Register of the Poland. Poselstwo (Netherlands) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Poselstwo (Netherlands) records,
1920-1940
59032
Poland. Poselstwo (Netherlands)
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Telegrams, logbook transcripts of telegrams, and memoranda, relating to Polish-Dutch relations during the interwar period. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/47/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/47/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Historical Note
Polish legation in the Netherlands.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of a good portion of the secret correspondence sent and received by the Polish legation in the Netherlands during the interwar period, relating to Polish-Dutch relations, as well as of memoranda in preparation for an international peace conference in the early 1930s. It serves not only as a good source for the study of the international tensions that led to the outbreak of World War II but also provides good coverage of the first two months of the conflict.
Of particular interest are the telegrams exchanged with Warsaw at the time of the Russo-Polish War of 1920, reflecting Poland's attempts to acquire arms in Western Europe and diplomatic moves to prevent an international blockade on deliveries by workers sympathizing with the Bolsheviks.
These records were formerly part of the Polish Foreign Ministry collection, acquired by the Hoover Archives in 1959, and were accessioned in the early 1990s as a separate collection.
A microfilm copy of these materials has been deposited in the State Archives of Poland in Warsaw.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Netherlands--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland.; Netherlands.; Poland--Foreign relations--Netherlands.
Series Description
- Decoded Reports, 1928-1931. (Box 1)
  Logbook of incoming and outgoing reports
- Decoded Telegrams, 1920-1929. (Box 1-2)
  Incoming and outgoing telegrams, arranged chronologically
- Decoded Telegrams and Letters, 1937-1939. (Box 2)
  Logbook of incoming and outgoing telegrams and letters
- Memoranda, 1931. (Box 2)
  Memoranda relating to preparations for an international disarmament conference, to Polish-German relations, and to conditions in Germany
Container List
- DECODED REPORTS, 1928-1931 (Box 1)
  - Logbook of incoming and outgoing reports, 1928 November - 1931 May (Folder 1: 1)
- DECODED TELEGRAMS, 1920-1929.
  Logbooks, unless otherwise noted
  - 1920 February 2 - December 31 (Folder 1: 2)
  - 1922 January 5 - 1923 July 14 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1923 July 16 - 1926 January 21 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1926 January 7 - 1929 July 17 (Folder 1: 5)
  - 1929 August 10-December(?). (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Loose leaves
- DECODED TELEGRAMS AND LETTERS, 1937-1939
  - Logbook of incoming and outgoing telegrams and letters, 1937 - 1939 October (Folder 2: 2)
- MEMORANDA, 1931. (Folder 2: 3)